Around a month ago, we had taken a look
at GitHub spec kit, an open-source
toolkit designed to help you get started
with specdriven development. This
approach can greatly improve both your
code quality and develop efficiency.
It's actually quite incredible because
it allows AI agents to focus directly on
specifications that are executable,
meaning they can generate real working
implementations, not just vibe code or
random suggestions that sound right but
don't actually run. Now, this framework
is truly impressive and it can greatly
elevate your coding workflow, bringing
structure, clarity, and precision as to
how AI collaborates with you. But the
main thing is spec kit works best for
brand new projects when you're working
from scratch. Once your code base
evolves, managing updates and changes
across specs become quite messy. It's
not ideal for ongoing development, but
that's where OpenSpec comes in. OpenSpec
is a new toolkit that builds on
specdriven development. It aligns with
humans and AI coding assistants on what
to build before any code is written.
It's quite lightweight and it's easier
to work with than spec kit. It requires
no API keys and it ensures your intent
is locked before implementation and it's
going to give you more deterministic
reviewable results instead of AI
guesswork. It keeps everything
structured with proposals, tasks as well
as spec updates, making scope changes
auditable and transparent. And unlike
different tool and unlike toolkits like
spec kit or something like Curo, which
shines for new features, openspec
evolves when modifying existing systems,
cleanly separating your current truth
from proposed updates. In short, it's
going to bring more control, clarity,
and reliability while being lightweight
to specdriven AI development at any
stage of your product. But you may
wonder, how does open spec compared to
these other toolkits like spec kit?
Well, the thing is it's able to handle
evolving features better with separate
folders for current specs and changes.
With Kurode, it is something that does
better at grouping all updates for a
feature in one place for easier
tracking. And if it's something that's
compared to something that doesn't have
any sort of specd driven toolkit, it is
going to ensure more predictable agreed
upon outputs instead of vague AI code
that is generated from a natural prompt.
And what's great is that it's supported
by many tools like cloud code, cursor,
open code, kilo code, codeex, and so
many others. And there's going to be
other tools that will be added soon like
root code when code. You even have
Gemini CLI. So apparently Zapier is dead
again, right? Every time a new AI tool
drops, people rush to say it's the end
of Zapier. But here's the truth. It's
never been more alive. Recently, we saw
the shiny new open AI tool, Agent Kit,
which is about answer optimization, not
workflow orchestration. It helps chatb
think better. But Zapier helps you do
more. Zapier doesn't just guess the
right answer. It orchestrates real
actions across 8,000 plus apps with
deterministic reliability. And guess
what? Zapier even plays nice with Open
AI's new MCP. So you can route answers
through Chhatbt and automate results
with Zapier. Zapier has been here
before. Platform native integrations, IP
pass tools, even chatbt itself. They
were all called Zapier killers. Yet here
we are still leading, still integrating,
still lighting the way for the future of
automation. And now with Zapier Cobbot,
you can describe what you need in plain
English and it will build a full
production ready workflow for you. Plus,
the new Opus Clip integration lets you
automate your video pipeline and
repurpose content at scale. So the next
time you see a Zapier killer, remember
Zapier isn't dying. It's redefining AI
orchestration. So use the link in the
description below so that you can build
smarter today. But now let's get started
and showcase how you can set this up. To
install this globally, you can use the
npm install command, but just make sure
you have the prerequisites installed
having the latest version of node. And
once you have that installed, we can
open up our terminal like command prompt
and then paste in the mpm install
command to install the openspec
globally. Once that is installed, you
can then verify the installation by
running the openspec version command.
See if it's installed, which it is. Now
we can initialize openspec into our
project directory. So, I've gone ahead
and I have created a template app for my
AI detection tool that I'm going to be
building out with this new openspec kit.
Now, what we're going to be doing is
initializing openspec within that
project directory. So, we can then paste
in the openspec initialize command which
will open up openspec for me. Now, it is
saying that you can configure openspec
with whatever AI assistant you want that
we had mentioned. So if you want to use
any of these different tools, you can
now specify which one you want to work
with. So you can click enter and then
you can select amongst these different
options like GitHub copilot, kilo code
or something like cloud code. I'm going
to actually use kilo code in my case. So
we're going to go ahead and click enter.
And after initializing it, you're going
to see a couple of new files within this
template for our AI detection tools.
Here it has created an agents MD file.
And essentially if you select the
supported tools say like cursor or cloud
code or something like kilo code in my
case opensp spec will automatically
configure custom slash commands and tool
specific instructions for that
particular AI agent. So this MD file
will then be handed off to my coding
agent and it's going to be associated
within my project file which you saw
that it had actually generated over
here. But now that we have everything
ready, the first step is where we're
going to populate our project context.
So what we can do is first copy this
natural prompt that openspec provides
and then we can go into whatever coding
agent we're working with. So in this
case we're working with kilo code. I've
gone ahead and added my folder as
context. And then I can send in this
prompt to read the openspec project MD
and help me fill out all the details
that are necessary about my project. And
you can see that the coding agent is
going to get the instructions to read
this file and make the necessary changes
for my text stack. So now you can see
that it has filled out all the necessary
details within the project MD with the
comprehensive details about my AI
detection tool. But now the next step is
where we're going to be able to give
openspec all the features that we want
it to thoroughly follow. So in this case
it is going to say that you copy this
prompt and then you add your features
over here like creating me the openspec
change proposal for this feature. So
right now I'm saying that I am building
an AI detection tool. Please create an
openspec change proposal for this
feature. And within that project MD
file, it is going to write up all the
necessary details that are needed for
the AI to follow in terms of the
architecture pattern, the state
management testing strategies and all
the necessary details that will make
sure that our app is proficient. So we
can then go ahead and send in our
feature request to kilo code, the agent
that will then execute it autonomously.
And the reason why I actually use kilo
code over any of the other AI coding
agents is because it's going to be able
to understand all the different commands
that would be necessary to use at any
point like using the opensp spec list
command to take a look at all the
different tasks that it has generated
and it will make sure that it will
process all of them individually
autonomously as well as keeping you in
the loop. And after it has generated all
the details for our proposal, it is
going to allow you to review through all
of these proposal files like the design
MD has generated all the different task
list where you can review through
everything and see if you want to
actually follow through with it. If
there's certain sections that you do not
want to work on, you can take it out and
add your own implementation. And
essentially this is the thoughtout plan
that it is going to work on deploying
with the agent to create your AI
detection tool or whatever you prompted
in the initial section. Now all you got
to do is just implement the change which
is what they specified within the GitHub
repository. So now I can just simply
instruct the AI agent to implement the
AI detection tool according to the
openspec proposal. all of these
different proposals that has listed in
terms of the design, the task list, as
well as the different specifications. I
also told it do not add any extra
features beyond what's specified. So now
we can have it work on tackling this
task. And you can see that it only
costed 48 cents in comparison to what
specit did, which took approximately, I
believe, 20 minutes to generate my
proposed plan for the task list that I
told it to generate. And it spent
probably around $5 I believe in my last
video which is a drastic difference from
this which is only 51. And as Kilo code
is working on executing this task of
generating our AI detection tool with
the specifications that the open spec
kit has developed we can actually go
within our terminal and we can run the
open spec view command. This will give
us a good understanding of the progress
of the generation right now. Right now
it is working on 46 different tasks. We
just started it. So as it progresses it
will give us visualization of all the
different changes being made. There we
go. It has finished generating our AI
detection tool. And this is what we have
gotten. This is where we can paste in
any sort of AI slop like this AI story.
And then we can analyze the text. And
you can see right away that it is
confident that this is AI detected,
which is true cuz I had it generated by
Chad GBT. And it talks about the
analysis of what is AI generated like
the different contents of this as well
as the metrics like the perplexity as
well as the burstiness. And all of this
was fully generated with kilo code
powered by openspec which is costing me
$2 to fully generate alongside with the
plan. And you can see how detailed it
was. made sure that it's functional in
one shot and it added all the necessary
things that we had requested like the
detection tool having different results
being analyzed and a lot more. This is
the power of openspec and I know the
front end doesn't look good but that's
just odd code or sorry cloud sonic 4.5
which doesn't really generate the best
frontends at the moment but you can see
that the quality is there in terms of
the output. If you like this video and
would love to support the channel, you
can consider donating to my channel
through the super thanks option below.
Or you can consider joining our private
Discord where you can access multiple
subscriptions to different AI tools for
free on a monthly basis, plus daily AI
news and exclusive content, plus a lot
more. But that's basically guys for
today's video on OpenSpec. This is a
pretty cool new tool that can turn AI
proposals into the structured reviewable
implementation plan that you can give to
whatever AI agent. It's lightweight,
which is why I really like it. And it's
something that you can easily work with
right away where you can seamlessly move
from specs to writing code a bit better
than any other AI coding agent. But let
me know what you guys think. This is
something that is completely free and
open source that you can easily get
started. So, I'll leave all these links
in the description below. Make sure you
go ahead and take a look at the second
channel if you haven't already. Join the
newsletter, join our Discord, follow me
on Twitter, and lastly, make sure you
guys subscribe, turn on the notification
bell, like this video, and please take a
look at our previous videos cuz there is
a lot of content that you'll truly
benefit from. But with that thought,
guys, have an amazing day, spread
positivity, and I'll see you guys really
shortly. He suffers.